David Clark Papers, Inclusive: 1992-2014, Bulk: 1995-2002
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
David Clark Papers
Inclusive: 1992-2014, Bulk: 1995-2002
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
32
Clark, David
1 document box
The David Clark Papers contain reports of Clark’s field trips and working sessions that illustrate how Bible translation flourished between 1992 and 2014, particularly in Russia, as well as related items, including photographs.
Administrative Information
Biography/Profile
David Clark was born in 1937 to a working-class family in Bristol where he won a scholarship to a grammar school and later to Cambridge. National Service in the RAF interrupted his schooling and included the Russian course at Crail in 1956 which proved providential many years later. After earning University degrees in classics and theology, Clark prepared for his calling in both scholarship and missions as a Bible translator.
In 1965-66, Clark, his wife, and young daughter lived in the bush with the Ekpeye people group in the Niger delta analyzing the language and helping create a writing system in preparation for Bible translation. His publication Babes in the Jungle: A Year of Life in the Niger Delta (Fontes, 2019) shares that experience which was foundational in writing his doctoral dissertation on the Ekpeye language at the London School of Oriental and African Studies.
Dr. Clark eventually became a translation consultant with the United Bible Societies and along with his family, spent 20 years in Thailand (two assignments), Papua New Guinea, and India. In 1991, the Clarks moved back to England to work in the European region, specifically in several former Soviet republics with a focus on minority Russian languages, including Yakut, Khakas, Tuvan, Kalmyk, and Chechen. He also served in shorter assignments with projects in Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, Belarus, Moldova, Ukraine, Azerbaijan, and Kyrgyzstan, some of which were initiated by UBS’ partner organization, the Institute for Bible Translation in Moscow. Clark retired in 2002 but continued part-time until 2009.
Materials in the collection include reports of Clark’s field trips and working sessions that illustrate how Bible translation flourished between 1992 and 2014, particularly in Russia, as well as related items, including photographs.
Scope and Content
The David Clark materials cover the period from 1992 to 2014 with the bulk from 1994 to 2002. The collection focuses on issues of Bible translation projects.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received David Clark’s materials that contain reports of his working sessions and field trips that illustrate how Bible translation flourished between 1992 and 2014. Photographs of those involved in the translations are also included.
The David Clark Papers are organized in three series: I. Correspondence, II. Europe Field Trips, and III. Languages.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 32.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Clark, David J., 1937-; Jinbashian, Manuel M.; Rudenko, Anatoly
Subjects
Bible -- Translating.; Chechen language.; Gagauz language.; Kalmyk language.; Khakas language.; Kyrgyz language.; Lezgin language.; Russian language.; Tuvin language.; Ukrainian language.; United Bible Societies.; Yakut language.
Genres
Correspondence.; Reports.
- Correspondence, 1995-1999; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Correspondence between David Clark and Manuel Jinbachian and Anatoly Rudenko on the topic “Russian Study” as well as correspondence with John Dean and the circulation list concerning a conference in Windsor, England. The series is in good condition.
  - Russian, 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Europe Field Trips, 1992-2000; 2
  Reports of trips made by David Clark to attend translation seminars in Russia, Ukraine, Norway, Iceland, Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, and Belarus. The series is in good condition.
  - Europe Field Trips, 1992, 1994, 1996 - 2000 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Languages, 1992-2014; 3
  The series contains reports of seminars and group meetings held for those involved in reviewing translations. The series is in good condition.
  - Bulgarian (correspondence, recommendations, reports, photos), 1992-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chechen (Meetings with the Chechen team regarding Genesis, Acts, John, Daniel, I Thessalonians, 2 Thessalonians, 1 & 2 Timothy, Titus, James, 2 Peter and Jude, Ephesians, Philippians, Colossians, and 1-3 John, Judges, Esther, and Ecclesiastes, Joshua and Revelation, Romans, Luke, 1 & 2 Corinthians, 1 & 2 Samuel, Ezra, Nehemiah, Joel, Amos and Obadiah, Psalms, Zechariah, Deuteronomy, letter written to support the application for asylum of a family involved for many years helping translate the Bible into the Chechen, photos), 2000-2005, 2008-2009, 2011-2012 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gagauz (Meetings with the Gagauz team regarding Luke chapters 1-7 and later chapters 8-24, Mark 3 & 7, Matthew 11, John 5, 12, 21, Acts 17-19, Ephesian, 1 & 2 Peter, Romans 9-11, Corinthians 8-11, 2 Corinthians 10-13, Titus, Hebrews 1-8, John, Jude, and Revelation 1-3, 20-22), 1995, 1997, 1999, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Kalmyk (Meetings regarding checking various chapters. Report from the Keston Newsletter and photos of David Clark with some of the translation teams.), 1997-1999, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Khakas (Meetings with the Khakas group regarding Matthew, Mark, Luke, John, Acts, Ephesians, 1-2 Thessalonians, 1-2 Timothy, Titus, Philippians, Revelation, Booklet of painting reproductions published by Vera Shugraeva in memory of her only son who was a gifted artist, photos of some of the translators), 1996-2007, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Kyrgyz (Meetings with translation team and discussion of Galatians, Philippians, Matthew, Mark, 1 & 2 Peter, Jude, 1 & 2 Thessalonians, 1 & 2 Timothy, Titus, James, Colossians, and photos), 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Lezgin (Meetings with the Lezgin Children’s Bible translators and checking teams for Matthew, Mark, John), 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Tuvin (Meetings with the Tuvin group regarding John, Matthew, Revelation, Ephesians, Colossians, 1 & 2 Thessalonians, 1 & 2 Timothy, James, 1 & 2 Peter, Jude, 1 & 2 Corinthians, Mark, Romans, Galatians, Hebrews, Acts, and Luke; discussion about the variety of meanings of words in John and Philippians, completed checking Revelation, Philemon, Titus and Matthew, work on checking Ephesians, Colossians, 1 & 2 Thessalonians, 1 & 2 Timothy, James, 1 & 2 Peter and Jude, Romans, Galatians, Hebrews, and completion of 1 & 2 Corinthians and the revision of Mark, discussion of gaps in Luke and Acts, follow up on Galatians, Romans, and Hebrews. Note: Tuvin New Testament released May 17, 2002), 1995, 1997—2000, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ukrainian (Translation seminar, work on Ukrainian translation, meeting with Ukrainian translators), 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Yakut (Meeting with Yakut group on Luke and John, Acts, Philippians, Titus, Matthew, 1 & 2 Thessalonians, Mark, Romans, Colossians, Revelation, 1 & 2 Corinthians, Hebrews, Psalms, Proverbs, article on Yakutia, and photos), 1994-1998, 2001-2002, 2005-2007, 2009, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 12)